Dorothy Woodruff Hillman Papers, 1916-1996
Sophia Smith Collection
Dorothy Woodruff Hillman papers
1916-1996
Hillman, Dorothy Woodruff, 1887-1979
MS 570
2 boxes (.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Teacher. Photographs, correspondence, and printed materials describing one year (1917-18) spent teaching the children of homesteaders at the Elkhead School in Routt County, Colorado.
Dorothy Woodruff (Hillman) was born in Auburn, N.Y., January 13, 1887, the daughter of Caroline Porter Beardsley and John Herman Woodruff. She attended Rye Seminary in Rye, N.Y., and graduated from Smith College in 1909. In 1916 she went to Routt County, Colorado with childhood friend and Smith College alumna, Rosamond Underwood, to teach for a year at the Elkhead School, built for the children of homesteaders who had come to settle in the Rocky Mountains. Woodruff later married Lemuel Serrell Hillman, with whom she had two daughters, Caroline and Hermione, and two sons, Serrell and Douglas. Throughout her life, Woodruff was active in civil and charitable work; she was executive director of the Grand Rapids (MI) chapter of the American Red Cross, and later became regional director for western Michigan. She died May 13, 1979.
Photographs, correspondence, and printed materials describing one academic year (1916-17) Woodruff and fellow Smith College alumna, Rosamond Underwood, spent teaching the children of homesteaders at the Elkhead School in Routt County, Colorado. The materials offer a small, compelling glimpse into rural life in the Rocky Mountains, as seen from the perspective of a young woman from the eastern United States.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection. This collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be difficult to use.
The Dorothy Woodruff Hillman Papers were donated to the Sophia Smith Collection Caroline Hillman Backlund and Hermione H. Wickenden in 2007.
Colorado--History--20th century--Sources; Rural schools--Colorado--History--20th century--Sources; Teachers--Colorado--Biography--Sources; Carpenter, Rosamond Underwood; Hillman, Dorothy Woodruff, 1887-1979; Carpenter, Rosamond Underwood
- Information provided by donor (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographs of Dorothy Woodruff 1917-18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Reminiscences by Woodruff: transcriptions undated (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
- Correspondence
  - Woodruff, Dorothy to family 1916-17 (originals and photocopies) (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Woodruff, John Herman (father) to Dorothy Woodruff, and to family 1903-17 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Third party 1916, 1974-76 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Elkhead School
  - Description by Dorothy Woodruff circa 1917 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Surveys 1917 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Student publication: ""Manhana" 1920 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Carpenter Ranch: article, and pamphlet 1948, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Underwood, Rosamond: eulogy, and photograph 1944, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Oversize Materials
  - Saturday Evening Post: article about Carpenter Ranch 12 Apr 1952 (Box 2)
  - Western Farm Life: article about Elkhead School 1 Aug 1918 (Box 2)